Guide to the Clipper Ship Card Collection 1858-1880, undated (Bulk 1850s-1860s) PR 116
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Clipper Ship Card Collection
1858-1880, undated (Bulk 1850s-1860s)
PR 116
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.35 Linear feet (1 box, 122 cards)
Clipper ship cards were printed to inform prospective passengers and freight shippers of a vessel's impending departure.
Provenance
Cards in the collection came from various donors (1911) and purchases: Naval History Society Fund (1962, 1963), Leonard Milburg Fund (1990).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Historical Note
The clipper ship was developed by American shipbuilders around 1840. "Clipper" was a generic term generally applied to very fast sailing ships; after about 1845 it became used to denote a standard rig and hull type and was used in conjunction with a word denoting the cargo carried or destination of the boat (tea clipper, California Clipper). The 1850s saw an increase in shipping and shipbuilding both within the United States and internationally. This was partly in response to new resources and new trading opportunities -- gold was discovered in California in 1849 and in Australia in 1850; 1849 saw the opening of the Asian tea trade.
The clipper ship's major attribute was speed. Before the advent of the clipper ship, sea journeys from New York or Boston to San Francisco took upwards of 300 days. Clipper ships were able to make the journey to San Francisco in 100 to 120 days. The return journey was a little quicker due to sea and wind currents. The clipper ship "Flying Cloud" set a record of 89 days to the west coast in 1851 and again in 1854. This record was tied by the "Andrew Jackson" in 1860. Speed did not always require a slim body construction: "Great Republic" was the largest and heaviest ship in the world when it was launched in 1853.
Production of clipper ship cards commenced in around 1852. They allowed shipping companies to directly advertise and circulate information about particular ships. These cards were handed out or mailed to prospective passengers or customers, and were often locally circulated by hand in the manner of handbills. Notices of ship availability and sometimes of sailing dates also appeared in windows and bulletin boards of agents and local shops.
The cards advertised the ship, shipping company, and other important information, such as the port of embarkation. Each card usually had an illustration of the vessel or its namesake. A few cards were decorated with stylized text of the ship's name, or a non-related (yet often nautical) image. Often, if not specific to the ship's name, the printed image could be used again for a different vessel.
The vast majority of clipper ship cards claim the vessel will sail "shortly." Although passengers were desirous of an exact sailing date, it was often difficult for the sailing companies to maintain a firm date. Often ships needed to be full in order to depart and thus were dependent on other sea-going vessels for shipments of cargo, as well as on an adequate number of passengers. The language on clipper ship cards shows the competitiveness of the industry. Cards make much use of superlatives; ships are touted as being the fastest, most beautiful, swiftest, or world renowned. The small size of ships was often highlighted as a desirable feature, in part because smaller ships could sail faster.
Technological advances in printing made it possible to print cheaply in color onto the enamel-coated surface of cardboard from about 1840. Clipper ship cards were letterpress printed on this coated stock, often overprinted with three to seven colors. Only a very few cards were lithographed. George F. Nesbitt, printer of the majority of these cards, is also known as the printer of the first U.S. government stamped envelopes. He worked from the corner of Wall and Water streets in the heart of New York's shipping district.
Clipper ship cards were mainly produced during the decline of the clipper ship industry, when companies needed advertising to drum up business. An economic depression in the middle 1850s, and the ensuing panic of 1857, lowered the profits of the shipping industry. The early 1860s was the time of the heaviest clipper ship card issuance. The heyday of the clipper ship can be dated roughly as lasting from the 1840s to the late 1860s, as the completion of the transcontinental railroad in 1869 helped to make clipper ships obsolete for passenger travel. Clipper ships were abandoned as cargo ships by 1881, largely in favor of steamships.
Historical information on specific clipper ships and printers of cards is available in the Department's Clipping files.
General note
Bibliography
Forbes, Allan. "The Story of Clipper Ship Sailing Cards" Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society October 1949.
Roberts, Bruce. "Clipper Ship Cards: the High-Water Mark in Early Trade Cards." The Advertising Trade Card Quarterly (date unknown.)
Shadwell, Wendy. "American Clipper-ship cards." The Ephemerist March 1981: 180-181.
Shadwell, Wendy. "Commercial Printing and the Maritime Industries." American Maritime Prints. Ed., Hall, Thomas. Portsmouth, N.H.: The Old Dartmouth Historical Society, 1985.
Shadwell, Wendy. "George F. Nesbitt: Maritime Specialist." Billheads and Broadsides: Job Printing in the 19th-Century Seaport. New York: South Street Seaport Museum, 1985.
Shadwell, Wendy. "A Selection of A-1 Clipper Ship Cards." The Lookout October/November 1980.
Scope and Content Note
The Clipper Ship Card Collection spans the period from 1858-1880 and contains examples of 19th century maritime advertising. The cards advertise commercial ship sailings, most are for clipper ship trips between New York and San Francisco. The collection contains 122 different cards issued for 102 ships. The largest card is 8 13/16 x 5 13/16 inches in size; the smallest is 5 5/16 x 3 inches; the average size is about 6 ½ x 4 inches. The Collection was removed from the Graphic Arts File (PR 022) in 2002. Cards are housed in alphabetical order by ship name. An index of cards organized by shipping company follows this finding aid. A searchable database with detailed description of each card is available in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections.
Most cards do not advertise the year in which they were sailing. Cards in the collection issued by Boston's Glidden & Williams Lines are unique in that they include a year printed as part of the sailing date.
Most of the cards advertise routes from New York to San Francisco. Four are to Australia ("Fred Warren" and "Web-Foot" from Boston, "Eureka" and "Game Cock" from New York). Eight advertise travel to Europe ("Circassian," "Ericsson," "City of Rome," "Helvetia," "Old Dominion," and three unnamed ships.) Several other routes are represented. The "Drew" sailed from New York to Albany, the "Gen'l Whitney" from New York to Boston, and the "Gen'l Grant" from New York to New Orleans. The "Arizona" sailed, appropriately enough, from New York to "Arizona, Wyoming, Nevada, Wisconsin, Alaska, Oregon."
New York printers include George Nesbitt and [W.] Endicott & Co. Boston printers include Rand Avery & Co., Watson's Press, and Fred Rogers. Well-represented New York shipping companies include Babcock, Cooley & Co., Cornelius Comstock & Co., John I. Earle & Co., Randolph M. Cooley, and Wm T. Coleman & Co. Shipping agents advertised include Sutton & Co. in New York and De Witt, Kittle & Co., and Albert Dibblee, both of San Francisco.
The four "Prima Donna" cards show portraits, in several cases identified, of European opera singers who performed in the United States. The card for "S.S. England" has a saloon plan on the verso.
Arrangement
Cards are filed alphabetically by ship name.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Clipper ship cards may also be found in the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 31).
Andrew Jackson (Clipper-ship); Arizona (ship); Asterion (ship); Aureola (ship); Belvedere (Ship); Black Hawk (Clipper ship); Blue Jacket (Ship); Celestial Empire (Ship); Challenger (Ship); Champion (Ship); Charger (Ship); Circassian (Steamship); City of Rome (Ship); Comet (Clipper ship); Conqueror (Ship); Cremorne (Ship); Daniel Marcy (Ship); David Crockett (Clipper ship); Derby (Clipper ship); Don Quixote (Ship); Dreadnought (Ship); Drew (Steamship); E. Southard (Ship); England (Steamship); Enterprise (Clipper ship); Ericsson (Steamship); Eureka (Ship); Franklin (Clipper ship); Fred Warren (Ship); Galatea (Clipper-ship); Game Cock (Ship); Garibaldi (Ship); General Grant (Steamship); General McLellan (Ship); General Whitney (Steamship); Golden Fleece (Ship); Governor Langdon (Ship); Governor Morton (Ship); Grace Darling (Ship); Great Republic (Bark); Harriet (Clipper ship); Haze (Ship); Helvetia (Clipper ship); Hornet (Clipper-ship); I.F. Chapman (Ship); James R. Keller (Ship); John Gilpin (Ship); Kate Bayes (Ship); Kentuckian (Ship); Ladoga (Ship); Lady Washington (Ship); Live Oak (Ship); Logan (Ship); Lookout (Ship); Malay (Clipper ship); Manitou (Ship); Marmion (Clipper ship); Mary L. Sutton (Clipper ship); Mary Robinson (Ship); Mattapan (Ship); Memnon (Ship); Messenger (Clipper Ship); Mindoro (Ship); Moonlight (Clipper ship); Morning Star (Ship); Neptune's Car (Clipper Ship); Nesbitt, George F. firm, New York, printer; Ocean Express (Ship); Ocean Telegraph (Ship); Old Dominion (Ship); Orpheus (Ship); Parsee (Ship); Polynesia (Ship); Prima Donna (Ship); Rand, Avery & Co., printer; Richard S. Ely (Ship); Robin Hood (Clipper ship); Rogers, Fred, 1832-1870; Sam G. Glover (Ship); Sea King (Ship); Shatemuc (Ship); Shooting Star (Ship); Skylark (Ship); Smyrniote (Ship); Snow Squall (Clipper ship); Sparkling Wave (Ship); Storm King (Bark); Susan Fearing (Ship); Susan Howland (Ship); Sweepstakes (Ship); Syren (Clipper ship); Thatcher Magoun (Clipper ship); Twilight I (Ship); W. Endicott & Co., printer; War Hawk (Ship); Watson's Press (Boston), printer; Web-Foot (Ship); Whistler (Ship); White Swallow (Ship); Windward (Ship); Wizard King (Ship); Zouave (Ship); Advertisements; Advertising–Shipping–United States; Cargo ships; Clipper ships--Pictorial works; Ephemera; Lithographs; Passenger ships; Sailing cards; Singers–Portraits; Wood engravings
  Scope and Contents note
  Cards are arranged alphabetically by ship advertised. If more than one card exists per ship, each card is identified by the image on the card or other distinguishing information.
  - Andrew Jackson [bust], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andrew Jackson [riding horse], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andrew Jackson [standing next to horse], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arizona, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Asterion, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aureola, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belvedere, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Black Hawk [Indian of North America holding bow], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Black Hawk [Indian of North America, bust], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blue Jacket, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Celestial Empire, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Challenger, 1859 Jan. 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Champion, 1859 Apr. 01 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charger, 1865 Feb. 04 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circassian, [1860] Jul. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circassian & Ericsson, [1860] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - City of Rome, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Comet, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conqueror, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cremorne [Mermaid holding framed drawing of clipper ship], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cremorne [Text with Stars and Moon in background], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Daniel Marcy, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David Crockett [Davy Crockett battling Indians of North America], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David Crockett [Davy Crockett with dog and rifle], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David Crockett [Clipper ship flying American Flag], [1861] Apr. 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Derby, [1858] Dec. 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Don Quixote, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dreadnought, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drew, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - E. Southard, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - England (S.S.), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Enterprise, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eureka [Samuel Stevens Crest], 1863 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eureka [text in gold on green card], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Franklin [Benjamin Franklin bust], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Franklin [Benjamin Franklin surrounded by inventions], [1860] Dec. 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fred Warren, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Galatea [American Flags], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Galatea [Galatea plunging into water], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Game Cock, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Garibaldi [Garibaldi with sword backed by soldiers], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Garibaldi [Garibaldi and soldiers riding towards canons], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gen'l. Grant, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gen'l McClellan, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gen'l. Whitney, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Golden Fleece, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Governor Langdon, 1863 Jul. 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gov. Morton, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grace Darling, 1864 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Great Republic, 1858 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hale, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harriet, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Helvetia, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Helvetia (S. S.), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hornet [Ship firing upon another ship, misprint], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hornet [Ship firing upon another ship], 1866 Jun. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - I. F. Chapman, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - James R. Keller, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Gilpin, [1862] Apr. 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kate Bayes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kentuckian, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ladoga, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lady Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Live Oak, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Logan [Indians of North America on rocks, in canoe, printing error], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Logan [Indians of North America on rocks, in canoe], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lookout, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Malay, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manitou, 1858 Oct. 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marmion, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marmion & Ocean Express, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mary L. Sutton, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mary Robinson [Girl with grapes in hair, colored image], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mary Robinson [Girl with grapes in hair, black and white image], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mattapan, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memnon, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Messenger, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mindoro, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Moonlight, [1858] Nov. 06 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Morning Star, [1861] Apr.06 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Neptune's Car, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ocean Telegraph, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Old Dominion, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Orpheus, [1860] Jul. 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Parsee, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Polynesia, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Prima Donna [Marietta Piccolomini and [?] DeWilmcast], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Prima Donna [Marietta Piccolomini], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Prima Donna [ [?] Colson, Angiolina Bosio, Marietta Alboni, [?] LaGrande], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Prima Donna [4 unnamed women], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Richard S. Ely, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robin Hood [Robin Hood blowing horn in forest, men in background], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robin Hood [Robin Hood leaning on tree, clipper ship in background], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sam G. Glover [Text with green ink], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sam G. Glover [Text without green ink], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sea King, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Shatemuc, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shooting Star, [1865] May 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Skylark, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Smyrniote, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Snow Squall, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sparkling Wave, [1859] Mar. 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Storm King, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Susan Fearing, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Susan Howland, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sweepstakes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Syren, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Thatcher Magoun [Male bust], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Thatcher Magoun [Beehive], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Twilight, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - War Hawk, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Web-Foot, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Whistler, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - White Swallow, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Windward, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wizard King, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Zouave, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Steamship surrounded by smaller boats], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Steamer with flags], 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [California Line of clipper ships], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Sloop, Brigatine, Brig, Cat Rig, Ship, Bark], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)